《猩球崛起》
嘿 好的... 现在...
Hey, okay... now...
我们再来一次
let's go again.
- 这是哪只? 9号?  - 是的 9号 亮眼睛
- Which one's this, number9?  - Yeah, number 9. Bright eyes.
你看到了吗?
Are you watching this?
这 这简直是难以置信
This, this is unbelieveable.
天啊
Oh, my God.
- 他用了几步?  - 20步
- How many moves was that?  - 20.
最完美的做法是15步 天啊 你给她吃了什么?
The perfect score is 15. God, what, what are you giving her?
嘿 把那个录像给我!
Hey, give me that video!
9号大猩猩 我们只给了她一剂药剂
Chimp number 9, just one dose.
- 你能等等来吗?  - 我们已经准备好了
- Couldn't I see you later?  - We're good to go.
我一会儿再打给你 嗯 好的 谢谢 再见
I'm going to call you back. Yeah, all right.  Thanks, Bye.
112号药剂 它有用
112, it works.
- 只是在一只灵长类动物身上生效?  - 一只就够了
- On just the one primate?  - One is all we need.
认知能力的完全恢复
Full cognitive recovery.
我们准备好了
We're ready.
你确定自己没有太心急吗?
Look, are you sure you're not rushing this?
我已经研究这个五年半了
I've been working on this for five and a half years.
这些数据很清楚了 我们准备好了 史蒂芬
The data is clear. We're ready, Steven.
现在就差你批准人体试验了
All I need is your approval for human trials.
这个啊 你需要董事会的批准
Oh, for this, you're going to need the Board's approval.
这个项目上投资了很多钱 威尔
There's a lot of money riding on this, Will.
- 你只有一次机会  - 一次就够了
- You only get one shot.  - One shot is all I need.
好的 我需要看你所有的研究成果
All right. I'll need to see all the research.
好的!
You got it!
- 还有 威尔...  - 嗯?
- Oh, and Will...  - Yeah?
不要把你的私人感情牵涉进来
Keep your personal emotions out of it.
那些人投资要看到成果 而不是梦想
These people invest in results, not dreams.
好的!
Okay!
来见见9号猩猩 她正在完成一个叫卢卡斯塔的游戏
Meet chimp 9. Here she's tasking at what is called the Lucas Tower.
这个游戏的目标是要把这个塔从一根柱子移到另一根柱子
The object of which is to move the tower from peg to peg
在这个过程中大盘不能放在小盘上面
without placing a larger block on top of a smaller block.
正如我们预料的一样 她完全无法完成这个谜题
As expected, she was unable to complete the puzzle at all.
后来 我们给她注射了名为ALZ-112的药物 这是一种
Then, we gave her what we call, ALZ-112, a gene therapy
可以让大脑创造细胞进行自我修复的基因药物
that allows the brain to create its own cells in order to repair itself.
在生物学中 这叫神经形成
In biology, this is called neurogenesis.
这里 在GEN-SYS
Here, at GEN-SYS,
我们把它叫做治疗老年痴呆症的神药
we call it a cure to Alzheimer's.
- 唐尼 你让她准备好了吗?  - 她怯场了
- Donnie, you get her ready?  - She's got stage fright.
是吗?
Is that what it is?
嘿 猩猩
Hey, ape.
她要把我的手都弄断了!
She's gonna break my arm!
亮眼睛! 放手!
Bright Eyes! Let go!
你还好吗?
Are you all right?
我们已经准备好进入下一阶段了
We're ready to move on to the next phase.
人体试验
Human trials.
给你 亮眼睛 你最爱的气泡苏打水
Here you go, Bright Eyes. It's your favorite fizzy soda.
来吧 准备好 唐尼
Come on, let's go, Donnie.
我们得把她搞到楼下去了
We should have her downstairs already.
好的 好姑娘!
Okay. Good girl!
出来吧 姑娘 对了
Come on out, girl, that's right.
这是给你的
That's for you.
抓住她!
Got her!
天啊!
Jesus!
唐尼 把笼子打开! 打开! 打开!
Donnie, open the cage! Open up! Open up!
我要给她打镇定剂了!
Going to sedate her!
- 不要!  - 把门关上!
- No, no!  - Get the door!
不要! 等等! 就现在!
No, no! Hold it! Now!
呼叫支援! 唐尼 唐尼!
Call help! Donnie, Donnie!
目前112号药剂只出现过
There have been absolutely no side effects associated
一种副作用
with 112, with one exception.
由于某种原因
For some reason,
猩猩的虹膜上出现了绿色的斑点
the chimps irises exhibit flecks of green.
其实 我们最初是在9号猩猩上注意到它
Actually, we first noticed it in chimp 9,
所以才给它起了"亮眼睛"这个外号
hence her nickname, Bright Eyes.
一会儿你们就会看到她
You'll see when we bring her in.
让开!
Move!
理论上 这种药物可以
In theory, this therapy can be used
治疗很多不同种类的脑科疾病
to treat a wide range of brain disorders.
它的潜力是无限的
It's virtually limitless.
可以给我们带来巨大的收益
As are the potential profits.
所以我们有信心
Which is why we are confident that
你们会批准人体试验的
you will vote to approve human trials.
不要!
No, no, no!
雅各布斯先生 雅各布斯先生 我求你了
Mr. Jacobs, Mr. Jacobs I am begging you,
我求你了 别这么做
I am begging you, not to do this.
听我说 其实只要花一小笔钱
Look, it costs a small fortune to
就可以给这些猩猩做一个检测
run lab workups on all of those chimps
但结果显而易见
only to tell me what I already know,
它们都被感染了
that they are contaminated.
这事关它们的生命啊
There are lives at stake here.
这些动物有个性
These, these are animals with personalities,
有感情
with attachments.
- 感情?  - 是啊
- Attachments?  - Yeah.
我这是在做生意 不是在开宠物园
I run a a business, not a petting zoo.
用最省钱的方式把这些猩猩杀掉
Find the most cost effective way to put those apes down.
我做不到
I can't do that.
你是猩猩管理员
You're the chimp handler.
那就解决问题
Handle it.
史蒂芬!
Steven!
刚刚的事真有趣!
Well, that was fun!
他们把112号药剂带走了
They've taken the 112.
董事会驳回了你的提案
Board has rejected your proposal.
他们选择开发别的项目
They've chosen to advance other programs.
你总能做点什么的吧
Well, there must be something that you can do.
是的 我可以把你炒了
Yes. There is, I could fire you.
相信我 我们已经谈过了
Believe me, we talked about it.
我们有五年令人信服的数据
We have five years of conclusive data.
这些数据随便你怎么处理
Parade all the data you want,
你再也无法说服任何人对你投资了
you will never convince anyone to invest another dime.
这种药有救命的潜力!
This drug has the potential to save lives!
更像是让公司破产的潜力吧
Bankrupt this company, more like.
我发誓 你对人类大脑了解得那么透彻
I swear, you know everything about the human brain
但就是不知道别人的想法
except the way it works.
从头开始研究112号
Go back to the drawing board on the 112.
从分子阶段重新开始
Start again in molecular development.
试着在别人研究出来之前成功
Find a way to get there before someone else does.
还有 收拾好这烂摊子
And, clean up this mess.
富兰克林!
Franklin!
这只很小 我们把她带来的时候
It's very small. She must have been
她肯定已经怀孕了
pregnant when we brought her in.
所以她才...
So that's why...
她不是进攻性强 她只是想保护她的孩子
She wasn't being aggressive. She was just being protective.
她以为我们想伤害她的孩子
She thought we were going to hurt her baby.
我本来想自己领养它
I would take it myself,
但是我小舅子在保安处工作 他肯定会把我供出来的
but my brother-in-law works for security. He'd rat me out in a second.
你要我领养它?
What, you want me to take it home?
我不知道怎么照顾猴子
I can't take care of a monkey.
- 他不是猴子! 他是猩猩  - 富兰克林...
- He's not a monkey! He's an ape.  - Franklin...
你只需要照顾他几天
You know, it's just for a couple days until
我会找到一个避难所 这就够了
I find a sanctuary. That's all I need.
富兰克林 不行!
Franklin, no!
这不是我的责任范围
Look, this isn't my responsibility.
这是公司财产
This, this is company property.
好吧...
Okay...
这样吧 博士
I tell you what, Doc.
雅各布斯让我把另外12只都杀了
Jacobs made me put down the other 12.
我干完了
I'm done.
你请便吧
Be my guest.
- 嘿!  - 哦 嗨
- Hey!  - Oh, hi.
- 你看上去精神不好  - 是啊 他怎么样了?
- You look beat.  - Yeah. How's he doing?
时好时坏吧
Well, he has good days and bad days.
今天不怎么样 不过
Today, not so good, although he
他开始背诵莎士比亚的剧本了
has been quoting Shakespeare.
哦 你搞来了一只宠物?
Oh, you got a pet?
嗯 他只在我们家暂时留宿几天
Uh, it's just a temporary house guest.
好吧 也许这对他有好处
Well, maybe that'll be good for him.
晚安!
Good night!
嗨 爸爸!
Hi, Dad!
爸爸?
Dad?
威尔! 我没听见你进门
Will! I didn't hear you come in.
就今天了 对吧?
Today's the day, right?
你以为我会忘记吗?
You thought I'd forget?
你今天有场大考 对吧?
You have a big test today, right?
化学?
Chemistry?
嘿 爸...
Hey, Dad...
- 我给你看样东西怎么样?  - 什么?
- You want to see something?  - What?
那是什么?他 受伤了吗?
What is that? Is he injured?
不 我觉得那是胎记
No, I think that's a birthmark.
"对凯撒 只有跪下 跪伏并惊叹!"
"As for Caesar, kneel down, kneel down and wonder!"
别太投入感情了
Yeah, don't get too attached.
他真可爱 是吗?
He's a cute little guy, isn't he?
我的车钥匙呢?
Where's my car keys?
我的车钥匙 你把它们放哪了?
My car keys, where'd you put 'em?
爸... 你已经不开车了
Dad,...you a, you don't drive anymore.
我知道
I know that.
来...
Here...
你来喂他吧 你会吗?
Why don't you feed him. Can you do that?
当然 我会...
Of course, I can..
威尔! 快来看!
Will! Look at this!
他多大了? 一天? 两天?
How old is he? Like, a day old? Two days old?
是啊...
Yeah...
他真聪明 是吧?
He's a smart one, isn't he?
你打算给他取什么名字?
What are you going to name him?
我不知道...
I do not know...
三年后
很快 凯撒展现了非常高的智力水平
Right away, Caesar displayed signs of heightened intelligence,
所以我收养了他 然后开始在家里工作
so I kept him. And, brought my work home.
十八个月后 凯撒认识24个单词了
By 18 months, Caesar was signing up to 24 words.
两岁时 凯撒可以完成
By age two, Caesar completing puzzles and models
为八岁及以上的儿童设计的游戏
designed for children eight years and up.
三岁时
At age three,
凯撒继续展现高超的认知技能
Caesar continues to show cognative skills
比同龄人类都要强
that far exceed that of his human counterpart.
家... 家
Home... home.
他以15步的满分成绩完成了卢卡斯塔
He completed the Lucas Tower in 15 moves, a perfect score.
我还是有几个假设: 一 他眼睛中的绿色斑点
I maintain my hypothesis that: A. The green in his eyes indicate
说明了ALZ-112从母亲遗传到了孩子身上
that the ALZ-112 was passed genetically from mother to son
二 由于大脑中没有受到损伤的细胞
and, B. That in the absence of damaged cells that need to be replacing
他体内的药物刺激了他的大脑功能快速发展
the drug in his system has radically boosted healthy brain functioning.
而且...
And,...
他下象棋很强
he plays chess pretty well.
爸!
Dad!
- 对不起  - 我再也做不到了
- I'm sorry.  - I can't do this, anymore.
他应该被送到养老院里去
He belongs in a home.
这样他根本没法过
This is no way for him to live.
没法过?
No way to live?
我把灯都打破了...
I broke my lamp...
这会让你好起来的 爸
It'll make you better, Dad.
爸!
Dad!
陶德 进来吃早饭
Todd, come inside for breakfast.
我会记录我从实验室带来的东西
I'll need to keep track of what I take from the lab,
不过我觉得你一个月注射一次就够了
although I don't see you needing more than one treatment a month.
这太神奇了!
Something amazing has happened!
我需要做个血液测试 一次扫描...
I'll need a blood test, a scan and the dosage...
还得控制用药量
carefully monitored.
如果我能溜进...
Now, if I can sneak...
威尔! 我已经好了!
Will! I'm not sick, anymore!
没事的 爸
It was nothing, Dad.
凯撒 凯撒在哪? 我要见他
Ceasar. Where's Caesar? I want to see him.
凯撒!
Caesar!
他肯定没有走远
He can't have gone far.
凯撒!
Caesar!
爸比!
Daddy!
凯撒!
Caesar!
滚出去! 滚出去!
Get out of here! Get out!
滚出去!
Get out!
嘿嘿嘿... 够了! 够了!
Hey, hey, hey... Enough! Enough!
不管你做什么
It doesn't matter what you do.
如果再让我发现有动物出现在我家门口 或者接近我的孩子们...
If I catch that animal anywhere near my house or my kids, again...
他不危险的
He's not dangerous.
不会有下次了
It won't happen again.
是的 不会了!
Damn right, it won't!
- 走吧 爸  - 他只是想玩玩
- Come on, Dad.  - He, he just wanted to play.
待在家里! 爸爸保护你们
Stay in the house! Daddy's got you.
我跟你说不要一个人出门
I told you not to go out without us.
没事...
It's okay...
情况多糟糕?
How bad is it?
我不知道
I do not know.
- 他喜欢你  - 嗯
- He likes you.  - Uh, huh.
别担心 马上就好了
Don't worry. It'll be over soon.
然后我们一起去搞点东西吃
Then, we can go get a treat.
我想 冰淇淋怎么样
I'm thinking, ice cream.
好主意!
Good idea!
你教他打手语?
You taught him to sign?
只教了一些基础的东西
Just, handful of things, basic stuff.
他在说什么?
What's he saying?
没什么
Nothing.
那么你觉得我们什么时候该来复诊?
So, when do you think we should come back?
你们不用再来了
Well, you won't need to come back.
这些线是可溶的
because, um, the stiches are dissolveable.
注意一下有没有感染的症状就好了
I would just say, watch for signs of infection.
发烧啊... 发红啊...
Fever... redness...
好吧 他现在在说什么?
Okay, what's he saying, now?
嗯
Um,
其实...
well,...
他觉得我们俩应该一起吃晚饭
he thinks that you and I should have dinner together.
我就知道...
I... know...
凯撒! 来吧!
Caesar! Come on!
卡洛琳 又见到你了 真好
Good to see you, again, Caroline.
你也来吗 凯撒?
You coming, Caesar?
你的秘诀是什么?
So, what's your secret?
其实这不是我的功劳 他的基因比较好
Oh, I can't take any credit. It's in his genes.
我觉得你太谦虚了
I think you're being very modest.
他真的很惊人
He's pretty amazing.
我觉得你为凯撒造的家真的很不错
I think you've built a pretty good home for Caesar, here.
这维持不了多久了
You know he won't stay this way for long.
他马上就会长大
He's going to soon grow into
变成一只巨大 有力量的动物
a large, powerful, animal.
过来!
Come here!
他怎么样了?
How's he been doing?
还不错吧
Okay, I think.
我爱猩猩
I love chimpanzees.
我也挺怕他们的
I'm also afraid of them.
怕他们也是自然的
And, it's appropriate to be afraid of them.
凯撒不会伤害别人的
Caesar will never hurt anyone.
他在这里很快乐
He's happy here.
嗯 看得出来
Yeah, I see that.
我们至少应该给他一点自由活动的空间?
We can at least give him some open space?
是啊 这应该不错
Yeah. That would prpbably be a good idea.
我知道 过了桥有个好地方
I know a place right across the bridge,
红树林 像天堂一样美丽
The Redwoods. It's a paradise.
过来!
Come on!
来这
Come here.
不需要绳索了! 没问题 快过来!
Doesn't need a leash! He'll be fine. Come on!
- 仅仅为了安全考虑  - 来啊 凯撒!
- Just to be safe.  - Come on, Caesar!
这就是红树林
It's the redwoods.
凯撒!
Caesar!
好吧
All right.
我把它解开 但是你不可以离开我的视线
If I take this off you can not leave my sight.
不然我就再也找不到你了
I'll never find you again.
好吧
Okay.
- 这是什么?  - 他在做什么?
- What's this?  - What's he doing?
- 我简直不能相信!  - 怎么?
- I don't believe that!  - What?
他在征得你的同意
He's asking your permission.
这是一个恳求的手势
It's a supplicating gesture.
没关系的
It's okay.
去吧 凯撒! 去玩吧!
Come on, Caesar! Off you go!
看他多高兴!
Look at him go!
凯撒!
Caesar!
- 凯撒!!  - 凯撒!!
- Caesar!!  - Caesar!!
凯撒!
Caesar!
你在这啊...
There you are...
凯撒!
Caesar!
去吧 凯撒 爬上去!
Come on, Caesar, climb!
再高一点!
Go higher!
爬啊!
Climb!
小心点!
Be careful!
凯撒 小心点!
Caesar, be careful!
五年后
你好啊!
Hi!
怎么了 伙计?
What's going on, buddy?
来碰下
Give some love.
来啊 小宝贝
Come on, honey.
那是只猩猩吗?
Is that a chimpanzee?
别这样!
Come on!
来!
凯撒! 凯撒!
Caesar! Caesar!
过来!
Come on!
别计较 过来
It's all right. Come on.
快来!
Come on!
我们走吧
Let's go.
你要进去吗?
Are you getting in?
凯撒...
Caesar...
你没事吧 朋友?
You okay, pal?
你是宠物吗? 不是
Are you pet? No.
你不是我的宠物
You're not a pet.
我是你的父亲
I am your father.
凯撒是怎么来的?
What is Caesar?
好吧...
Okay...
凯撒 这里是我工作的地方
Caesar, this is where I work.
也是你出生的地方
This is were you were born.
当时你母亲和她的同伴都在这里
Your mother was here with other chimpanzees.
但是她现在不在这了...
But she's not here, anymore...
所以...
so...
我才把你带回家和我一起生活的
that's why I took home to live with me.
是的
Yeah.
你的母亲死了
Your mother's dead.
实际上 她被注射了药物
The thing is, she was given medicine,
正如我给查尔斯注射的药物一样
like the medicine I give to Charles.
她把它遗传给了你
She passed it on to you.
所以你才会这么聪明
That's why you're so smart.
我们带他回家吧
Let's take him home.
来吧 解释一下
Come on, explain it to me.
好吧
All right.
为了让他活命 我把它偷偷带出实验室
I snuck him out of the lab to save his life.
我没想到药效会被母亲遗传给它
I had no idea that the effects had been transfered vertically from his mother.
但从那时起 他就表现出了不可思议地高智商行为
But, since then, he's been displaying incredible signs intelligence.
我设计了112号药剂用来修复 但凯撒的表现远超出预期
I designed the 112 to repair, but Caesar's gone way beyond that.
这是他去年以来的智商表
Here's his IQ from last year.
到现在 他的智商提高了一倍
Since then, it's doubled.
这一切都是错的
This is all wrong.
我的父亲曾经不能自理 这药剂让他重获新生
My father was on gone. This drug brought him back.
你没见过他有多么糟糕
You never saw how bad he was.
他拥有了正常的生活
He has his life again.
- 那凯撒怎么办?  - 什么怎么办?
- And, what about Caesar?  - What about him?
他怎么生活下去?
How does he fit in?
和我... 和我们一起...
With me... with us...
听着...
Listen...
我知道这对你来说很难
I know it has been hard for you,
但是你在试图操控我们绝对不应该插手的事情
but you are trying to control things that were never meant to be controlled.
112号药剂是有效的
The 112 works.
你意识到你有多疯狂吗?
Do you realize how you sound?
我只是说它是很棒的东西
All I'm saying is this is a good thing.
凯撒就是证明
Caesar's proof of that.
我父亲也是
So's my father.
凯撒 吃点东西吧
Caesar, eat your food.
爸 你还好吗?
Dad, are you okay?
我很好
Yeah, I'm fine.
抗体
Antibodies.
他的免疫系统找到了对抗112病毒的方法
His system has found a way to fight the 112 virus,
因此它没办法发挥疗效
so that it can't deliver its therapy.
我父亲的病会更严重的
My father's disease is going to return with a vengeance.
停下来!
Stop!
停下来 马上!
Stop, right now!
嘿! 离开那! 从车里滚出来!
Hey! Get out there! Get out of that car!
你他妈的在干嘛? 从我的车里滚出来!
What the hell are you doing? Get out of my car!
我说了 从我的车里滚出来!
I said, get out of my car!
我是飞行员! 我得赶去机场!
I'm a pilot! I've got to get to the airport!
现在我怎么去那里?
How am I gonna get there now, huh?
回答我的问题! 你到底在干什么?
Answer the God-damn question! What were you doing?
我有台一模一样的车...
I have a car just exactly...
我完蛋了... 警察会来处理的
I'm done... the police can handle it.
就待在这! 你哪都不能去 先生!
Stay right there! You aren't going nowhere, mister!
你会付出代价的!
You will pay!
这是你的问题 你造成了现在这种局面!
This is your problem, you make it happen!
我跟你没完! 就待在这!
Not through with you! Stay right there!
凯撒 停下!
Caesar, stop!
爸爸!
Daddy!
凯撒!
Caesar!
我没事
It's okay.
没事了
他不是故意的
He didn't mean it.
别害怕...
It's okay...
嗨 把那玩意拿下来!
Hey, hey, take that thing off of him!
把那玩意拿下来!
Take that thing off of him!
听着 我来它带进去 好吗?
Look, I'll take him in, okay?
不行 法院命令扣押他 我们不能放开
No, he's under court orders. We can't do that.
没关系! 随他吧
It's fine! Let him.
你准备好的时候再带他进来
Bring him in when you're ready.
拿下来
Take it off.
谢谢!
Thank you!
凯撒 凯撒 凯撒... 凯撒 凯撒
Caesar, Caesar, Caesar... Caesar, Caesar.
现在还不是时候 但一切都会好的
Not right now. It's going to be okay.
我们就进去看看里面什么样子
Let's just see what it's like inside, okay.
来吧 凯撒
Come on, Caesar.
我们走
Let's go.
来吧... 相信我
Come on... trust me.
还不错
It's okay.
去吧
Go.
他从来没和其他猩猩相处过
He hasn't spent any time with other chimps.
这种情况我们见多了
Oh, we're used to that.
刚开始他会有点暴躁敏感 但是我们会让他融入进来
He'll be a little skittish at first, but we'll integrate him.
他们能很快适应环境
You'd be surprised how quick they adapt.
我们提供了适宜的生存环境
We provide a stimulating environment.
他会在这愉快地生活下去
He's going to thrive here.
过来 我们签写书面文件吧
Come, let's do some paperwork.
进来之前确保把门锁上
Make sure you lock that door when you come in.
凯撒!
Caesar!
你会没事的!
You'll be okay!
一切都会好起来的!
Everything's going to be okay!
别害怕
Don't be scared.
目前 你要待在这里
You're going to stay here, now.
不... 还不能回家
No... Not going home right now.
别拖拖拉拉了
It's OK.
道别拖得越久
The longer you drag out the good-byes,
就会变得越难
the harder it is.
我能待会再签吗?
Can I sign that later?
你的思念可能会更深
You'll probably miss him more than he'll miss you.
最好给他几周适应环境
You'd best give him a couple of weeks to get used too the place.
威尔 我们得走了
Will, we have to go.
我们得回家了
We have to go home.
我们很快会再回来的 好吗?
Coming back soon, okay?
来之前打个电话
Just call ahead, before you do.
嗨 过来!
Hey, over here!
我能救你出来!
Hey, I can get you out!
过来! 来这边!
Come on!  Over here!
下来
Hey, down here.
蠢猴子...
Stupid monkey...
你还不过来? 搞定他!
So you? Come on, make it!
法庭判决还没下来 因此系统里没有记录
Court order hasn't been filed, so it's not in the system.
一旦有消息
Once it comes through,
在你收到上诉日期前差不多要90天
it will take about 90 days before you receive an appeal date.
- 90天?  - 没错 先生 90天
- 90 days?  - Yes, sir, 90 days.
你将收到邮件通知
You'll be notified by mail.
这才是接下来要发生的事
Here's what's going to happen.
你再到你的电脑里好好查查 然后给我个
You're going to go back to your computer, you know, shift things around
确切的上诉日期 这周内的 明白了吗?
and you're going to get me a date for my appeal, this week, you got it?
我无能为力
I can't help you.
好吧 那你有麻烦了
All right, then we have a problem.
因为除非你照我说的做 我不会走的
Because, I'm not moving until you do.
90天 先生 能有上诉日期你就偷笑吧
90 days, sir. Be thankful you're talking about court dates.
没有弄死你的猩猩已经很幸运了
You're lucky they didn't put that animal down.
我保证很快把他带回来 爸爸
I promised to get him back soon, Dad.
爸爸?
Dad?
我父亲的免疫系统一直在抵触112号病毒
My father's immune system continues to reject the 112 virus,
导致基因疗法不起作用
rendering the gene therapy obsolete.
他的健康状况不断恶化 并且疾病发展迅速
his health is deteriorating, and the disease is progressing rapidly.
我需要一种更具攻击性的病原体
I need a more aggressive virus strain,
一种能更快发生作用的方法
a faster delivery method,
因为在这个时候...
because at this rate...
我不能同时失去他们
I can't lose them both.
我不会失去他们的
I won't lose them both.
嗨... 能聊聊吗?
Hi... Can we talk?
快点 我还有会议要参加
Make it fast.  I've got a meeting.
十年来你一直在经营GEN-SYS公司
The ten years you have been running GEN-SYS,
流水线上制造出来的多少种药物可以拯救无数人的生命?
how many drugs have come down the pipeline that could save millions of lives?
可以改变一切?
That could change everything?
你在说什么?
What are you talking about?
ALZ-112号
The ALZ-112.
你怎么了 威尔?
What happened to you, Will?
曾经你是这个实验室的明星 而现在你几乎不露面
You used to be the star of this lab. Now, you hardly ever show
当你出现的时候 你也在浪费自己和团队的时间
and when you do, you waste your time and that of your team's
研究一种药物
fixating on a drug
在那些事情发生之后 这研究就不可能有任何前景
that, after what happened, is never ever going to get approved.
112号药剂很危险 威尔
The 112 is dangerous, Will,
而且它不管用
and it doesn't work.
我用它治好了我的父亲
I treated my father with it.
它确实有作用
It does work.
你做了什么?
You did, what?
你到底做了什么!?
You did, what!?
战胜了疾病 正如我们预期的那样
Beat the disease, like we predicted.
太棒了
Brilliant.
但有一个复杂的问题
There's been a complication.
它是否真的起作用了?
Well, does it work or doesn't it?
我父亲的病比疗效更来势汹汹
My father's disease eventually outran the cure.
噢 上帝保佑
Oh, for goodness sake.
免疫系统会产生抗体来对抗这种病毒组织
The immune system produced antibodies to beat the viral component,
但它会起作用的
but it will work.
我已经研制出了一种病原体
I've have already developed a virus strain
它会更具攻击性
that I think will be more aggressive.
你这么认为?
You think?
只要让我做些测试
Just, let me test it.
你在浪费我的时间
You're wasting my time.
还有更多改进!
There's more!
疗效将会比疾病速度更快
The applications go beyond the disease.
有数据显示这种疗法可以提高认知系统
There are indications that show the therapy can improve cognitive functioning,
记忆能力...
memory quality...
什么 你在说什么?
What, what are you saying?
我的父亲不仅仅恢复了
My father didn't just recover.
他变得更健康了
He improved.
你指的是提高智力水平?
You mean, increased intelligence?
还没有定论 但确实是这样
It's not conclusive, but yes.
我要你立刻在猩猩身上实验修复后的112号药剂 越快越好
I want you, to start testing the revised 112 on chimps, A-S-A-P.
好的
Okay.
我会给你一切你要的东西 只要你立刻开始
I'll give you whatever you need, but get started.
吃晚饭了!
Dinner time!
大猩猩 灵长类!
Great Ape, primate!
来吧 看到这玩意还不知道吃吗?
Go on, don't you know food when you see it?
你觉得很有趣?
You think that's funny, huh?
我来告诉你什么叫做有趣!
I show you something funny!
你马上就会知道谁是老大
You'll learn who's boss, soon enough.
他还穿着衣服怎么办?
What about his clothes?
衣服怎么了?
What about 'em?
我不知道... 可能会被其他猩猩当作异类
I don't know... May cause problems with the other apes.
好极了!
Good!
一共十只猩猩 没错吧?
I counted ten apes, correct?
是的
Yep.
好 都运到后面去
Good.  All the way to the back.
你们行动太快了 着什么急啊?
You guys are moving really quick on this. What's the big rush?
第一天复工 你依然在抱怨
First day back, you're still complaining.
科巴 你好 我是威尔
Koba. Hi, I'm Will.
就他了
This one.
他很冷静
He's very calm.
是的
Yeah.
他经历过很多实验 他知道规矩
He's been through a whole lot of labs. He knows the drill.
我能加入吗 看看你们的进展
Could I join you, what's our progress.
让他准备好
Get him prepped.
戴好面罩
Tighten your masks.
把113号递给我
Pass me the 113.
脉搏很有力 血压稳定
Pulse-ox is good, blood pressure is steady.
药物注射剂 到位
Perisol delivery, in place.
释放113号
Releasing the 113.
有泄露!
We have a break!
富兰克林 戴好面具!
Franklin, get your mask on!
搞定了?
Got it?
是的
Yeah.
还好吧?
You okay?
是的
Yeah, okay.
都起来动一动!
Move it!  Let's go!
都起来运动运动 你们这些懒狒狒!
Get up and do some exercises you lazy baboons!
智力测评结果非常棒
Intelligence results are remarkable.
没有不良反应
There are no adverse effects.
猩猩们有惊人地强大免疫系统
Apes have amazingly strong immune systems.
好的 好好照顾他
All right, keep an eye on him.
没问题
Okay.
抱歉
Sorry about that.
这些家伙比我还有抵抗力
These guys are more resiliant than I am.
我出去一下
Excuse me a second.
你伤得严重吗?
You seriously injured?
你知道手语吗?
Do you know sign language?
我在马戏团工作
I worked at the circus.
好了
He's good.
小心点 人类不喜欢有智商的猩猩
Be careful. Humans do not like intelligent apes.
你今晚要工作到很晚
You're working late tonight.
GEN-SYS公司还需要三只猩猩
GEN-SYS needs three more.
嘿 凯撒!
Hey, Caesar!
你受伤了吗?
Are you hurt?
给我看看
Show me.
凯撒 把手给我 把手给我
Caesar, give me your hand. Give me your hand.
有时候 新来的总会被教训一顿
Sometimes, the new kid on the block gets picked on.
保持冷静 他们做了什么?
Stay calm. What did they do?
扯淡!
That's bullshit!
这里出什么事了?
What's the problem here?
我要带他离开这里 马上
I'm taking him out of here, right now.
没有法院命令不可以带走
Not without a court order, you're not.
他再也不是你的了
He's not yours, anymore.
我发誓 如果我发现他受到任何形式的虐待
I promise, if I find out he's been mistreated in any way,
我会让这地方关门
I'll have this place shut down.
随你便...
Go on...
不 我们不能马上回家
No.  No, we're not going home, right now.
我会带你离开这里的 我保证
I'm going to get you out of here, I promise.
你一定要相信我
You have to trust me.
凯撒 你一定要相信我 好吗?
Caesar, you have to trust me, okay?
探视结束了
I think this visit's over.
相信我
Trust me.
你会没事的
You'll be okay.
快点 走啦! 我们走!
Come on, move it! Let's go!
这里有成百上千只猩猩! 好像你有了私人动物园一样!
There are hundreds of them! Looks like you're own private zoo!
更像是这些毛茸茸家伙的监狱
Rather like a prison for hairy dudes.
他们会看电视?
They watch TV?
我们管这叫提升
We call it enrichment.
哦 这只真可爱!
Aw, this one's so cute!
他叫什么名字?
What's his name?
叫柯妮丽娅 她是母的
Uh, name's Cornelia. It's a she.
天啊!
Oh, my God!
别靠太近!
Don't get too close!
这只把我吓得半死
This one scared me half to death.
那只大家伙叫毛里斯
That big guy is called, Maurice.
没意思
It's no fun.
来 我给你看点有意思的
Here, I'll show you something fun.
看看这个!
Check this out!
太疯狂了!
It's crazy!
你不该在这里
You shouldn't be in here.
嘿 下个就是你!
Hey, you're next!
好了 我们走吧
Come on, let's go.
看样子 我们在这里花了太多时间了
We spent too much time in here, as it is.
走吧!
Come on!
看看这家伙
Check out this guy.
阿兰 他不是好惹的 他觉得自己很特别之类的
Hey, Alan, he's a pain in the ass. He thinks he's special, or something.
捉摸不透的!
Freaky!
嘿 过来
Hey, come here.
我觉得他在想些什么
I think he's thinking or something.
天啊 他抓住他的喉咙了!
Oh, my God, he's got him by the throat!
放开他!
Let him go!
放开!
Let go!
你没事吧?
Are you okay?
没事
Yes.
我说过不要靠太近的 兄弟
I told you not to get too close, man.
走吧 各位 我们出去吧
Come on, guys, let's get out of here.
有些事不需要被改变
Some things aren't meant be changed.
你需要接受它
You need to accept that.
嘿!
Hey!
这里出什么事了?
What's going on here?
再做些113号药剂的试验 我们在做准备...
More 113 trials. We're just prepping...
不 我们必须先分析科巴的血液!
Oh, no, we have to analyze Koba's blood work first!
富兰克林知道流程 他在哪?
Franklin knows this. Where is he?
他请了两天病假
He's out sick for two days.
我没有批准这次试验
Well, I didn't authorized this.
不!
No!
我批准的
I did.
我们同意在一只猩猩上做保守测试
We agreed to test sparingly on one subject.
那只猩猩太令人吃惊了!
And, that one subject is stunning!
这是种病毒 我们不知道它对人类的影响
It's a virus. We don't know the human related effects.
药物起作用了 威尔
The drug works, Will.
告诉他 琳达
Tell him, Linda.
开始 科巴以15步的满分成绩完成了卢卡斯塔
For starters, Koba scored a perfect 15 on the Lucas Tower.
每次测试的结果都验证了它的有效性
Every test result verifies its effectiveness.
- 不能再测试了  - 你在...
- No more tests.  - What are you...
在我们弄明白我们在做什么之前 不能继续
Not until we have a better understanding of what we're dealing with.
听着 我会明确告诉你我们做的是什么 听着...
Look, I'll tell you exactly what we do. Look...
给我几分钟
Give us a minute.
麻烦一下! 把猩猩放回笼子里 温柔点
Excuse me! Put the ape back in the cage. Be gentle.
威尔 我明确告诉你我们在这里做的是什么
Will, I'll tell you exactly what we're dealing with, here.
我们在研究一种药物
We're dealing with a drug that is worth more
它比我们研究合成的任何药物都更有价值
than everything else we are developing, combined.
你创造历史
You make history,
我挣钱
I make money.
- 这不就是我们的安排吗?  - 不! 这有风险
- Isn't that our arrangement?  - No! There are risks.
你别跟我讲风险
Don't you tell me about risks.
你给你自己爸爸吃试验阶段的药物
You give your own father an experimental drug.
我一通电话就能结束你的职业生涯
I could finish your career with one phone call.
我给你省点麻烦吧 我退出
I'll save you the trouble. I quit.
没有你 我们也会继续的
We will proceed without you.
听着... 你不知道自己在做什么
Look... You do not know what you're doing.
这些测试应该被限制
These tests need to be contained.
你根本不知道113号药剂是否稳定
You have no idea if the 113 is stable,
它会对人类造成怎样的伤害...
what kind of damage it can do to people...
所以我们先在猩猩上做试验... 不是吗?
Well, that is why we test it on chimps... isn't it?
罗德曼博士 是我 富兰克林! 我要跟你谈谈!
Dr. Rodman, it's, me, Franklin! I need to talk to you!
你可以开门吗?
Can you come to the door?
博士!
Doc!
你到底是谁?
Who the hell are you?
离开这里!
Get out of here!
对不起... 对不起
I'm sorry... I'm sorry.
你不会是想收买我吧?
You wouldn't be trying to entrap me, would you?
这个... 我不敢说同意
Well... I can't say that I approve.
他们不是人 你知道的
They're not people, you know.
你放不放他走?
You gonna to let him go or not?
凯撒... 嘿 过来
Caesar... hey, come on.
来吧 我们回家
Come on, we're go home.
回家
Home.
过来 我们真的要走了
Come on, we're really going.
我们离开这里
Let's get out of here.
对... 来吧
Yeah... Come on.
凯撒?
Caesar?
我猜和自己的家相比 他更喜欢这里
I guess he likes it better here with his own kind.
为什么发曲奇饼 火箭?
Why cookies, Rocket?
一只猴子... 很弱
A single monkey... is weak.
猴子们聚在一起... 就有力量
Monkeys together... a force.
猴子都是没脑的
Monkeys are stupid.
妈的 罗德尼
Damn it, Rodney,
你又把水管留在中房了?
You leave the hose out in the atrium, again?
什么? 没有!
What? No!
来吧! 我们走
Come on!  Let's go.
快点 起来!
Come on, Get up!
在发射八个月后
Eight months after its launch,
地球的首个飞向火星的载人飞船...
Earth's first manned space flight to Mars...
我不会逃避 我说的是事实
I ain't dodging. I'm telling the truth.
好吧 如果不是我拿的曲奇饼
Yeah, well, if I've didn't take the cookies,
还能是谁干的?
then, who the hell did?
我 我不知道...
I, I do not know...
嘿! 你们俩傻子别闹了!
Hey! Will you two morons knock it off!
我回家了
I'm going home.
星球表面有水 这样才能维持生命
Covered in water and therefore able to sustain life.
该死的猩猩房都比你俩太平
I get more peace in the God-damned ape house.
爸爸 对不起!
Dad, I'm sorry!
富兰克林先生 我是多蒂!
Mr. Franklin, it's Dottie!
富兰克林先生... 有人吗?
Mr. Franklin... Hello?
怎么回事?
What the hell?
罗德尼 立刻到猩猩放风的地方来
Rodney, get to the platform, now.
罗德尼!
Rodney!
你他妈的以为你在干嘛?
What the hell do you think you're doing, huh?
进去!
Get!
走啊!
Go on!
回到你的笼子里去!
Get back in your cage!
我在警告你!
I'm warning you!
走啊 进去!
Go on, get!
就这样吧!
That's it!
这是你自找的! 回去!
That's what you get! Get back!
你怎么了?
What's wrong with you?
臭猴子!
Dumb monkey!
把臭爪子松开 你个脏猩猩!
Take your stinking paw off me, you damn dirty ape!
不!
No!
我会打死你们每一个
I'll beat each and everyone of you.
卡洛琳 你去过凯撒的房间吗?
Caroline, have you been up to Caesar's room?
没有人接
No one's answering.
兰登!
Landon!
威尔!
Will!
出什么事了?
What happened?
他说话了
He spoke.
你说什... 什么?
What are you...what?
你的猩猩... 他说话了
Your ape... he spoke.
怎么回事?
What in the hell?
我不相信
I don't believe this.
我会打死你们每一个
I'll beat each and everyone of you.
我需要有人联系旧金山警察局
I need someone to coordinate with the S.F.P.D.
告诉他们 有人死了
Tell them we got a fatality.
怎么了?
What is it?
我知道他去了哪里
I know where he's headed.
格兰?
Glenn?
我们走!
Let's go!
雅各布斯
Jacobs.
雅各布斯先生 我是威尔团队的琳达
Mr. Jacobs, It's Linda from Will's team.
听着 有可怕的事情发生了
Look, something terrible has happened.
富兰克林死于病毒感染
Franklin is dead from a viral infection.
你到底在说什么?
What the hell are you talking about?
他吸入过113号药剂 它对猩猩
He was exposed to the 113. It does something
没有副作用 对人类却有
to people that it doesn't do to apes.
我们必须穿过城市 横过大桥
We'll have to go through the city and across the bridge.
雅各布斯先生? 雅各布斯先生 你在听吗...
Mr. Jacobs? Mr. Jacobs, are you...
怎么回事?
What the hell?
我是史蒂芬·雅各布斯!
I am Steven Jacobs!
这里到处都是猩猩 我得上直升机!
It's full of apes in there. I gotta get in the air!
我们必须有能力毁灭他们
We have to be able to destroy them.
这件事就相信我吧! 好吗?
Just, trust me on this! Okay?
你应该把相机准备好 一般来说
You might want to get your cameras ready. Normally,
这些家伙是非常害羞的
these guys are quit shy.
他们去了北边的公园!
They're going the park, on the north side!
找到领头的!
Find the lead!
你要抓着按钮! 按钮!
You gotta hold the button! The button!
他们被引领了 这些猩猩比你想的要聪明
They're being led.  These apes are smarter than you think.
他们有一个领袖!
They've got a leader!
别跟他们说我堵车了 找个好点的理由!
Do not tell them I am stuck in traffic. Make up with something smarter!
坚持住
Hold on.
他们的...
What the...
他们在桥上
They're on the bridge.
他们想去红杉树林
They're trying to get to the redwoods.
旧金山警局 一号直升机
SFPD, Police 1.
这里是空中指挥部
This is Air Ops,
封锁南端桥头 那些部队的情况怎么样?
seal of south end. What's the status of those units?
准备就绪 长官
Ready to go, sir.
一旦他们到了你那里 就拦住他们
As soon as they reach you, block them.
北端 我们会把他们赶到你那里
North side, we're going to push them right to you.
没问题 我们已经准备好了
No problem. We're ready for them.
北端封锁 他们绝对不能通过这里
The north side is blocked. They'll never get through here.
一旦他们进入封锁区域 我们就干掉他们!
As soon as they hit the gap, we'll take them out!
- 你能直接杀死他们吗?  - 就像朝桶里的鱼开枪一样
- You can just shoot them?  - Like shooting fish in a barrel.
很好!
Good!
把车开回去!
Turn that thing around!
- 离开大桥 先生  - 我不能...
- Get off the bridge, sir.  - I can't...
是你不明白 离开大桥 马上!
You don't understand. Get off this bridge, now!
这里被封锁了 出去!
This is an evacuation. Get out!
所有市民安全
All the civilians, clear.
请确认
Please confirm.
让那些人离开大桥!
Put these people off the bridge!
准备就绪 城市骑兵!
Stand by, city mounted units!
他们会对猩猩进行大屠杀的
They're gonna slaughter them.
我要找到凯撒
I'm gonna to get Caesar.
威尔 嘿!
Will, hey!
你要小心!
You, be careful!
我要上我的车!
I gotta get to my car!
离开这里!
Get out of here!
放开我! 我必须上我的车!
Let go me! I have to get my car!
把他们往北赶!
Push 'em north!
别挡道!
Get out of the way!
快点 我们会在雾中跟丢他们
Hurry, we're going to lose them in the fog.
动手!
Do it!
他们在哪? 我没看见他们!
Where are they? I don't see them!
北端防护队 你们有看到吗?
CHP North, do you have a visual?
没有 长官 没看见
No, sir, negative.
打开保险!
Safety's off!
停止射击!
Hold your fire!
退后!
Back!
凯撒!
Caesar!
就是他! 他是领袖!
That's him! That's the leader!
他们出现了! 干掉他们!
They're in sight! Put 'em down!
救我!
Help me!
抓我的手!
Take my hand!
拜托...
Come, come on...
拜托!
Come on!
不救你...
Not you...
不!
No!
救我!
Save me!
凯撒!
Caesar!
凯撒?
Caesar?
凯撒... 对不起
Caesar... I'm sorry.
是我的错
This is my fault.
这必须结束
This has to stop.
不该是这样的
This isn't the way.
你知道他们有什么能力
You know what they're capable of.
回家吧
Please come home.
如果你回家 我会保护你
If you come home, I'll protect you.
凯撒回家了
Caesar is home.
Caesar's home.
走吧
Go.